(ALARM BLARING)
UNA: No matter how many stars
there are in the sky.
no matter how many galaxies
swirl beyond our own...
TERMINAL JOCKEY:
Tracking locked onto inbound UFO.
It appeared out of nowhere.
UNA:...no matter what
the mathematical probabilities
or the number of times we say
we are not alone in the universe...
TERMINAL JOCKEY:
It's closing in. but slowing down.
...our first visit from the stars
is always
the province of children's stories
and science fiction.
Talk to me.
TERMINAL JOCKEY: Telemetry is confirmed.
UFO is not of planetary origin.
It's from outer space.
UNA: First contact with aliens always
lives squarely in the impossible.
Getting stable visual.
UNA: First contact is just a dream...
- Oh. man.
- ...until one day it isn't.
What is that?
(WIND BLOWING)
KLAATU: The universe grows smaller
every day.
And the threat of aggression
by any group. anywhere.
can no longer be tolerated.
There must be security for all
or no one is secure.
Now. this does not mean
giving up any freedom.
- (COMMUNICATOR CHIRPING)
- Except for the freedom
to act irresponsibly.
Your ancestors knew this.
We of the other planets have
long accepted this principle.
We have an organization for
the mutual protection of all planets
and for the complete...
Really?
Again?
(CHUCKLES) Come on. it's a classic.
Mmm. More coffee. Captain Batel?
Mmm. Don't mind if I do. Captain Pike.
Still haven't decided?
Mmm. Enterprise is in Spacedock
for another week.
That's ages.
Pancakes were good.
(COMMUNICATOR CHIRPING)
- Phone's ringing again.
- Yep.
You ever gonna answer it?
(CHIRPING STOPS)
So. when do you ship out?
Chris.
We can keep doing this.
but we can also talk about it.
Talk about what?
Whatever it is you're
so busy not talking about.
Whatever happened out there.
Whatever's got you questioning
your return to command.
Whatever's got you questioning...
Yes?
Everything.
It's classified.
I've got deeper
security clearance than you do.
Not for this.
I ship out tomorrow at 0600.
- Back in a month.
- Hey...
I might still be here.
So give me a call. we'll get together.
That'd be nice. I'd like that.
But I really hope you're not.
You've got better places to be.
(COMMUNICATOR CHIRPING)
(ENGINE WHIRRING)
(HORSE NEIGHING)
You spooked my horse.
Apologies.
You weren't answering your communicator.
With all due respect. Admiral.
what the hell do you want?
I have a first contact scenario
that may have gone bad.
I'm sorry to hear that.
It's not my problem.
The officer in command
is someone I trust...
You're not hearing me. Bob.
We both agreed that I'd have
until Enterprise left Spacedock
- before deciding whether or not...
- But then we lost contact
- with her ship.
- I'm not sure what
- this has to do with...
- Here's her last transmission.
We haven't heard from her since.
First contact is just a dream.
Until one day it isn't.
I suspect a new world will be
joining the Federation soon.
Your first officer doesn't
do downtime well. Chris.
Mine used to be a lot like that.
(SCOFFS)
I'm pulling Enterprise
out of Spacedock.
She's still on scheduled maintenance.
She can skip
the redundant systems checks.
I want her crewed up
and ready to fly by 1800.
Send someone else.
You don't want me
in command of that ship.
You're getting us confused.
You don't want you in command.
What the hell happened out there. Chris?
It's classified.
Classified.
Look. I'm sympathetic
to whatever's going on with you.
But I want you to find out
what happened to Una.
You can quit when you get home.
but right now.
I need you back on that horse. Captain.
That's an order.
PIKE: Space.
The final frontier.
These are the voyages
of the starship Enterprise.
Its five-year mission.
to explore strange new worlds...
to seek out new life
and new civilizations.
to boldly go
where no one has gone before.
(THEME MUSIC PLAYING)
SPOCK: Query.
T'PRING: Response.
Vulcans are so formal.
- Aren't we. though?
- Query.
Response.
- Well said.
- Thank you.
Perhaps simply asking a question
rather than prefacing it
with a declaration
that a question is coming
would be more efficient.
- One would think.
- So?
You asked me here to this spot
on the anniversary
of our first courtship event.
You are wearing ritual mating colors.
So I am.
And yet the entire meal
has passed without you...
Querying?
Yes. Querying.
Without you asking me a question.
That's patently untrue.
I have asked you many questions.
About your family.
P'Sal's new lute recordings.
Your gallivanting about the galaxy
- with Starfleet.
- "Gallivanting"?
Is there a particular question
that you would like me to ask you?
Apologies.
I may have assumed too much.
I have been away.
which can mitigate tradition.
- I have no right to as...
- Query.
Spock.
Will you marry me?
I was beginning to think
you would never ask.
Which.
I now believe. was the idea.
I'm going to have to ask you two
to do that somewhere else.
Please.
What an excellent idea.
SPOCK: On Salon.
the seas consist of liquid mercury.
Earth's are water.
There's nothing out there
better than what's here on Vulcan.
Perhaps you need to show me.
(COMMUNICATOR CHIRPING)
- Don't.
- I have to.
- I took an oath.
- As you just did to me.
Matrimony and duty.
The two will complement each other.
I remain skeptical.
Spock.
Are you naked?
No. Captain.
No. Chris. he's not. He was about to be.
- It's a special night.
- Sorry.
Is everything all right. Captain?
We're going back out.
Number One's gone missing. Spock.
April's sending us to find her.
I will meet you on board. Captain.
T'Pring will understand.
- Pike out.
- Spock out.
That should have been a query.
Whether or not I would understand.
I am sorry.
Don't make a habit of it.
I won't chase you across the galaxy
just to get married.
There is no need to chase
what we already have. T'Pring.
(INDISTINCT RADIO TRANSMISSIONS)
Enterprise. this is Shuttle Stamets
incoming to transport coordinates.
WOMAN: (OVER RADIO)
Stamets cleared to transport.
(INDISTINCT RADIO TRANSMISSIONS)
All scrubbed up and good as new. sir.
Wish it were that easy.
Sir?
Energize.
(SOFT WARBLING)
- How are you. Mr. Spock?
- SPOCK: Systems are all nominal.
But as you know.
no simulations were run.
Thank you. Chief Kyle.
SPOCK: The main A.I. has been upgraded.
Personnel rotation was in process.
A few officers will have
to billet after the mission.
That includes the chief engineer
and Lieutenant Kirk.
whom I know you requested.
It seems like a million years ago.
Three months. ten days. four hours.
five minutes. actually.
I asked how you were. Spock.
I am well. Captain.
Although I confess each time
I return to space.
the weight I carry for the loss
of my sister feels heavier.
I'm sorry. I miss her. too.
Bridge.
- (DEVICE BEEPING)
- Okay. new cadets. medical...
Oh. good. we needed that.
Uh. security.
- Security...
- What is it. Captain?
Um. well. I just assumed
that in Una's absence...
Forgive me. Captain. Command believes
I would best serve the mission
as chief science officer.
No. I know. I understand. Spock.
I just. uh...
I just didn't think about having...
(BOATSWAIN'S WHISTLE BLOWS)
...a new Number One.
WOMAN: Captain on the bridge.
Captain Pike.
Lieutenant La'An Noonien-Singh.
Chief of Security.
I've been assigned
as acting first officer.
Welcome aboard. Number One.
You've got some
pretty big boots to fill.
I'm aware.
Okay.
Welcome back
and welcome aboard. everyone.
Ready. Lieutenant Ortegas?
You bet. Course for Kiley 279 plotted
and laid in. Captain.
- Ops. How we doing. Lieutenant?
- Lights are green across the board.
She feels ready to me. Captain.
Communications?
Ah. yes. the prodigy.
Cadet... Uhura?
On communications rotation.
Very happy to have you aboard.
Thank you. sir. Glad to be here.
(COMMUNICATOR CHIRPS)
Enterprise is cleared for launch.
Okay. Ortegas. let's take her out.
We are five-by-five for warp.
(FAINT MOANING)
Captain?
What?
Oh.
Right. of course.
Okay. Ms. Ortegas.
Hit it.
(ENGINES POWERING UP)
(WHOOSHES)
Ship-wide. Cadet Uhura.
- Aye. sir.
- (DEVICE CHIMES)
This is your captain.
We're a little early out of the gates.
so I hope we didn't catch anybody
with your hair wet or your pants down.
As you're all aware. Starfleet
send out a first contact team
whenever our deep space probes
detect signs
of a working warp engine.
Six days ago. the signature
of a functioning warp drive
appeared on Kiley 279.
The U.S.S. Archer went to say hello.
We have since lost contact.
Our mission is to find our people
and bring them home.
And maybe. if we get lucky.
make some new friends.
Nobody dies.
This mission will not
be anybody's last day.
- Captain out.
- (DEVICE CHIMES)
Let me know when we get there.
I'll be in my quarters.
Number One. you have the comm.
Aye. Captain.
Maintain course and speed.
AUTOMATED VOICE:
Alert. radiation leak detected.
Training exercise aborted.
WOMAN: I got this!
MAN: Get out of here!
AUTOMATED VOICE:
Four seconds to lockdown.
- (INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
- Three.
Aah!
AUTOMATED VOICE:
Radiation reaching critical levels.
- Emergency lockdown complete.
- MAN: Captain Pike!
Stop!
WOMAN: Captain Pike!
MAN: No!
(WOMAN GASPS)
(DOOR CHIMES)
Come.
Mr. Spock.
Captain. I do not wish to overstep.
Overstep.
Saurian brandy?
Are you yourself. sir?
Well. I'm very much myself.
That's the problem.
It was not lost on me
that when you went down
to the Klingon moon of Boreth.
you returned a changed man.
Boreth is notable for two things.
a monastery
and a rare ore that can cause temporal
consciousness displacement.
Both of which bear
the power of transformation.
It wasn't the monastery.
No. I assumed as much.
You saw the future?
I saw my own death. Spock.
At least the death of the man I am now.
I know exactly how and when
my life ends.
And I didn't just see it. I felt it.
Every agonizing second.
Most humans.
we like to think that
right until the very last instant.
somehow. some way.
we'll cheat death. (CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
At least I did.
Is it soon?
Only you could ask that question.
And no.
It's almost a decade away.
Is that soon?
Suddenly that feels soon.
I can't stop seeing it.
Sir. I would suggest knowledge of death
is vital for effective leadership.
Knowledge is one thing. Spock.
but I experienced it.
How will it live in me?
Will it make me hesitant?
Cautious? Not cautious enough?
I'm already second-guessing myself.
And that's the last thing
a captain can afford.
Suffering can be
transformed into insight.
You must seek out the good
in knowing your own death.
Use it to be the man
you most essentially are.
And who's that. Spock?
The captain.
(SPEAKER CHIMES)
UHURA: Captain Pike to the bridge.
We're dropping out of warp.
(FAINT MOANING)
Any sign of the Archer?
Getting her transponder ping
on the night side.
Take us around. Lieutenant.
- Hail her. All frequencies.
- Trying.
Nothing. sir.
Any chance we're losing her
response in sub-space chatter?
There is no sub-space chatter.
It's dead quiet out there.
We've got a visual. sir.
On screen.
MITCHELL: All systems show in the green.
Ship's perfectly intact. sir.
PIKE: Life signs. Mr. Spock?
SPOCK: None.
But neither am I detecting
any bodies. The ship is empty.
Where's her crew?
Fascinating.
I'm all ears.
It's a figure of speech.
I am remotely accessing
the ship's manifest.
Archer carried only Una
and two astrophysicists.
LA'AN: If she went to the surface.
she'd have headed
for the warp signature.
Can you locate it. Spock?
I have it. sir. Although...
Not really in the mood
for an "although" right now.
I'm having trouble locking on.
Its location may be shielded.
This warp signature's also got
a pretty weird signal variance.
Pretty weird?
Recommend deflector shields to full.
Any obviously defensive posture
is in direct violation
of first contact protocols.
No hails from the surface
or sub-space chatter.
No interplanetary traffic.
Not one orbital dock.
- What's your point?
- These people aren't showing
any signs of local space colonization.
Which puts them a century
behind constructing warp drive.
- Yet they have a warp signature.
- A nascent one.
- The anomaly is a red flag.
- Captain. there is not sufficient...
- Activate deflector shields.
- Aye.
- (SHIELDS POWER UP)
- (ALARM BEEPING)
ORTEGAS: Reading multiple launches
from the surface.
Plasma torpedoes. Three direct hits.
- Damage assessment?
- MITCHELL: Minimal.
But if we hadn't had our shields up...
Good call. Number One.
Take us up. Ortegas.
Maybe they'll think they got us.
What is going on down there?
Plasma torpedoes?
That's 21st-century tech.
How in the hell did these people develop
a faster-than-light engine?
They did not.
Recommend we go to red alert.
Red alert. Ms. Uhura.
- (ALARM BLARING)
- I have analyzed the signal variance
Lieutenant Ortegas isolated.
These people have not
built a warp drive.
Based on these readings.
they have built a warp bomb.
It would seem there are
two warring factions.
And their conflict has escalated
to a crisis point.
Surface scans of the planet
are consistent with pre-warp society.
- How is that possible?
- SPOCK: As you know.
the Vulcans invented first contact.
As they never fail to remind us.
The worlds in this sector with warp.
All have or are in process
of being inducted into the Federation.
We are free to travel to any of them.
General Order 1 does not apply.
Not on one of these worlds.
in fact. not once in the entire
history of first contact
has warp been first developed
as anything but a drive.
Put another way. the nuclear bomb
could have been invented
before particle physics.
- It simply never has been.
- PIKE: Would Number One have known
that the warp signature
was that of a weapon?
Possibly not. Our scanners
were just updated in Spacedock.
LA'AN: If those missiles are
the best they've got.
let's beam down. find our people.
and bring them home.
We have to consider the possibility
that this technology isn't native.
However they got it.
if they found it
in a crashed alien spacecraft.
if it was placed in their hands...
General Order 1 applies.
We cannot interfere
with their natural development.
- We cannot show ourselves for risk...
- But if they've already seen us?
We cannot risk the possibility.
So we just leave our people there?
Hardly.
Let's go see the doctor.
Doc.
Please. dispense some wisdom.
Okay.
Never get the house dressing.
(LAUGHS)
Ah.
Good to see you.
Dr. M'Benga toured the Mojave with me
and I toured Kenya with him.
Mr. Spock.
- And this is...
- A pleasure to see you again.
Of course.
You had to certify her for duty.
I received your orders. Captain.
This is Nurse Chapel.
Nurse Chapel is on civilian exchange
from the Stanford Morehouse
Epigenetic Project.
Sounds like you're
just the person for the job.
What job?
I'm gonna mess with your genome.
You first.
The locals are humanoid.
They're a close match
to most of the crews'
physiology and genetics.
But we'll need to make a few alterations
if you want to blend in.
Internally. they have
a bunch of different organs
that would take a lot longer to change.
so just try not to get an X-ray.
Change how. exactly?
Nurse Chapel is part
of Starfleet's initiative
to better observe alien cultures
without contamination.
You make disguises.
And you boss a rocket ship.
if. you know. we're going
all simplistic here.
I make minor alterations
to your genetic code
and induce internal celerity
to express short-term changes
to your biology.
Is it safe?
Almost every time.
Sedative first.
Your body is going
to undergo compressed.
jury-rigged metamorphosis.
It's painful.
Damn the ramparts. Doctor.
It means go ahead.
(CHUCKLES) Okay.
(DEVICE BEEPING. HISSING)
CHAPEL: I modified it for you.
But Vulcans are more complex
and your half-human genome is unique.
So...
it might not last as long
the first time.
No sedatives. Just the gene therapy.
CHAPEL: Maybe I wasn't clear about
the terrible pain part?
Maybe I wasn't clear when I said no.
So...
I've read your file. Um...
- I think I understand...
- Are you giving me
a direct order to allow sedation
during this procedure. Captain?
I am not.
Then I prefer to remain fully aware.
People survive things.
Well. there's surviving
and then there's living.
It's your choice.
Hang in there. sister.
(DEVICE BEEPING. HISSING)
Local clothing patterns
have been downloaded into the buffer
as well as universal translators
and tricorders.
- Confirming no weapons?
- Confirmed.
KYLE: Setting you down somewhere
with no foot traffic.
Just don't lose my socks. Mr. Kyle.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
Energize.
(SOFT WARBLING)
Why is it always an alley?
Captain.
Where are my pants?
(PIKE LAUGHS)
When in Rome. Mr. Spock.
Don't worry. It's not a dignity issue.
For the record. this was not my choice.
REPORTER: Protests carried on through
the night and into the morning
at federal sites around our nation.
Seditious elements
continue to spread rumors
of an advanced weapon being developed
by the government for domestic use.
Captain. it appears
we've landed in a society
in the midst of some
prolonged civil conflict
within this planet's government.
PIKE: Shades of old Earth.
Are you familiar with
the United States of America. Spock?
Yes.
As I am with both their civil wars
and their devastating results.
If this society's
already at a flashpoint
and they've somehow acquired
an advanced weapon...
- (BEEPING)
- LA'AN: Captain.
We're close enough
for me to get a better fix
- on the warp signature.
- PIKE: Where?
There.
(SHOUTING. CLAMORING)
Whatever is shielding the warp tech
makes transport impossible.
We can't beam into the building.
We'll have to find...
Captain. permission to act fast.
- Granted.
- Stay here.
(GASPS)
(GROANING) Please. Help me.
(WHIMPERING)
Oh. my medication... Over here.
- Easy.
- His neck.
SCIENTIST: What?
LA'AN: His neck! His neck.
(SCIENTIST GROANS SOFTLY)
It is fortunate their
musculature was responsive.
It's fortunate that you can
finally take a hint.
Enterprise can fabricate replicas
of their clothes and security badges
to match our retinal scans.
What do you suggest
we do with these two?
Beam them up.
- Beam them up where?
- Well. sickbay can sedate them.
You're suggesting we leave
these people unconscious
on a Federation starship
while we complete our mission?
They'd experience no pain.
have no memory. just some lost time.
(MACHINES TRILLING)
M'BENGA: They're both under
low-level sedation.
- Let's see how this works on them.
- CHAPEL: I need a DNA sample.
- M'BENGA: Right now?
- The simulation I'm running shows
that Spock's genetic coding
is beginning to deteriorate.
If I don't synthesize a booster
with actual Kiley DNA.
he may not pass a retinal scan.
You'd need one with
compatible surface proteins
for Mr. Spock's Vulcan blood.
Or he'll never get past security.
(MONITOR BEEPS)
This one's not going to work.
Looks like we got lucky.
Where am I?
(GRUNTING)
(WHIMPERS)
(GASPS. WHIMPERING)
BOTH: Delta Scorpii VII.
I'll prep the booster.
you catch the rabbit.
Always giving me the fun job.
Well. you're my favorite.
(PANTING)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
- (COMMS CHIMING)
- Ortegas.
M'BENGA: The landing party
needs to stand by.
Don't let them enter that building.
CHAPEL: And we got
a Delta Scorpii VII situation.
(SIGHS) Always when
I'm in the captain's chair.
That was quite a performance
you gave back there. by the way.
Prey posture.
Useful for tricking predators
into thinking you're helpless.
ORTEGAS: Captain. you can't go in.
What? Why... Why?
Chapel needs to beam down
a booster for Spock.
Give us a minute.
Hey. keep it moving.
We don't have a minute.
M'BENGA: Kyle.
can you pinpoint a location
and beam down and apply an eye salve?
Uh. are you kidding? No.
Transporters don't do that.
ORTEGAS: Chief. it's Ortegas.
Find a way to make them do that.
(PANTING)
Whoa. no. no. wait. wait. wait.
wait. wait. wait. wait. wait.
- Where the hell am I?
- I know you're scared.
- It's not what you think.
- What is this?
Okay. maybe it is a little bit.
No. no. no. no. come on!
(DEVICE BEEPING)
- Hi.
- (WHIMPERS)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(BEEPING. WHIRRING)
(BEEPS)
UHURA: We're headed to the bridge.
The bridge is where our Backtack is.
Like the game Tagball on your planet.
The Backtack makes all the decisions.
You know Tagball?
(GRUNTING)
I'm so sorry.
(SCANNER TRILLS. BEEPS)
- Where's the scientist?
- Headed for the bridge.
Can we fire up the emergency
medical transporter?
Energizing.
I heard the greatest match game
was Cone Rockets versus Boom Shield.
Yes. I was there...
CHAPEL: Gotcha.
Thank you.
Welcome to Enterprise. (KISSES)
Uh. Uhura.
Chapel.
(SCANNER BUZZES)
(INDISTINCT P.A. ANNOUNCEMENT)
Step away from the scanner.
M'BENGA: It's up to you now. Kyle.
I said step away.
(BEEPS)
Go on.
SPOCK: Captain. my genetic alterations
may continue to wear off.
LA'AN: Got her. This way.
The walls here are embedded
with some kind of highly dense
radiation plating.
It's why our sensors couldn't
penetrate the building.
Only something as powerful
as a warp signature
would even have a chance of getting out.
But now we're inside.
I can track her bio signs.
She's alive. Captain. And she's here.
- Where?
- Down.
Way down.
(ELEVATOR MUSIC PLAYING)
- (ELEVATOR BELL DINGS)
- This is us.
- Down here.
- Spock. your ears.
I'm aware. The pain is quite remarkable.
The recoding seems
to have stabilized for now.
(BEEPING INTENSIFYING)
It's this one.
(DOOR BUZZES. LOCK CLICKS)
UNA: Captain?
- That's quite a look.
- Really?
How about "Thank you for saving me"?
Somehow. I figured you might.
Can you move?
Projectile wound. result
of our less-than-warm welcome.
Minor altercation.
In retrospect.
we might also have considered...
(GROANS SOFTLY)...traveling incognito.
La'An.
Hey. Chief.
- Hate to be the other guy.
- Wait. you two know each other?
Yeah. she found me once.
when I was in a bad spot.
Didn't I tell you to stop being brave?
Captain. I should have said something.
- I...
- Later.
Spock. the shielding is jointed.
- We used a spoon.
- UNA: We may be able to route
a transport signal through the gaps.
Yes. if we were closer to the surface.
Number One.
- Yes. Captain?
Uh. the original.
Can you walk?
It is fortunate our route is empty.
Can you not jinx it?
- It is illogical to believe...
- (ELEVATOR BELL DINGS)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
SPOCK: Captain. the pain.
it is unbearable.
Spock?
(SCREAMING)
Ah. that's better.
(GRUNTING)
No time to hide them. Let's move.
(ELEVATOR BELL DINGS)
- (TRICORDER CHIRPING)
- SPOCK: Still too much interference.
- We have to get higher.
- What happened here?
These people are not ready
for first contact.
She's not cleared for this.
I don't give a damn.
How the hell did they get warp?
We gave it to them. Captain.
We're less than one light-year
out from Zero Point.
Zero Point?
Where we and the crew of Discovery
opened up a wormhole to the future.
Between Kelpien and Klingon ships.
there must have been
a hundred warp signs.
We lit up the sky.
And their various telescopes
were just good enough to see us.
They collected enough data
to reverse engineer
- a matter/antimatter reactor.
- (TRICORDER CHIRPS)
- Captain. I have Enterprise.
- They weren't ready for warp.
Not by a long shot.
And now they're using our tech
to build a weapon.
I never considered...
UNA: Chris. no one could have.
We were fighting for the very lives
that are in jeopardy now.
Pattern boosters are working.
UNA: We can't make them
care about the stars.
That's not our job.
Transporter control is locking on.
They just wanted to crush their enemy.
And we gave them the means.
(ALARM BLARING)
Found our sleeping friends.
Captain. we are ready to beam up.
MAN: Captain!
SPOCK: Captain.
If we leave now. every death
that follows is on our hands.
We cannot further influence
the destiny of this world.
Meant to or not. Spock. we already have.
Our only option now
is to influence it well.
Chris. General Order 1
clearly states we cannot in...
Screw General Order 1.
Spock. you're with me.
The rest of you get back to the ship.
- Captain.
- Right now.
That's an order.
Four to beam up.
Leave the captain
and the science officer behind.
(SOFT WARBLING)
Spock. on me.
Is this wise?
I am clearly alien.
That's what I'm counting on.
(ELEVATOR BELL DINGS)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
Take me to your leader.
PIKE: The failure was ours.
We owe your entire world
a profound apology.
You're saying our ingenuity was actually
- your mistake?
- PIKE: No. I'm saying
that we should've been more circumspect
about exposing our technologies.
A tenet of our people
is not to influence
less-developed civilizations.
How perfectly noble.
The power you're harnessing
can bridge the gap between worlds.
But its capacity for destruction
cannot be underestimated.
We have been in conflict
with a seditious faction
for centuries.
This is our opportunity
to end that conflict.
Through mass murder?
Have your people never
put down civil unrest?
Negotiation. Debate.
These are the tools
to build a lasting peace.
Tell me. are there groups
who refuse to negotiate with you?
Powerful groups?
Oh... Oh. yes.
- And with those?
- You remember when elephants fight.
it's the grass that suffers.
The Kikuyu people
of Kenya. Africa. on Earth.
they teach us that lesson every day.
You've given me a proverb.
which is less useful than a big stick.
Whoever has the biggest stick wins.
Well. our regulations compel me...
Your rules are not my rules. Captain.
My job is to ensure our ability
to govern future generations.
If spilled blood is the price.
so be it.
Take them.
What good is a rule
if you're not willing to die for it?
Or break it.
Emergency communication
from Captain Pike.
- (COMMUNICATORS BEEP)
- Enterprise to lower orbit.
Full visibility. Show 'em what you got.
- Captain?
- Wait for it.
(ALARM BLARING)
(INDISTINCT SHRIEKING.
CLAMORING IN DISTANCE)
PIKE: Just like you said.
whoever has the biggest stick wins.
In this case.
that is me.
Today. in a historic moment.
leaders of the governing
and revolutionary factions will meet
to discuss the arrival of the aliens.
This is the first time in a century
both leaders have been
in the same room at the same time.
And we will bring it all to you. live.
(BOTH SHOUTING)
LA'AN: This is going well.
They've become used to episodes
of violence for centuries.
The true cost of a civil war
is abstract.
Not believing you're gonna die
is what gets you killed.
What did you just say?
LA'AN: Sorry. Captain.
Just something my father said
not long before he...
Well. you read my file.
You know the Gorn captured
my family's colony ship
and deposited us on one of their
planetary nurseries.
Didn't understand
what he meant at first.
But I had a lot of time
to think about it.
About why I was the only one to survive.
Do you know what I saw on the faces
of so many of the people I loved
as they died?
Before they were slit open
and fed on alive
or used as breeding sacs?
Do you know the last thing they felt?
Surprise.
Yes.
Because right up until the last moment.
they couldn't imagine dying.
Yes.
But not you.
No. Not me.
And that's what kept you
alive.
Thank you. Lieutenant.
Captain.
I'm gonna need access
to the historical database.
- Cadet Uhura.
- (COMMS CHIRPING)
I need you to punch a signal
down to the planet.
(DOOR WHOOSHES OPEN)
(DOOR CLOSES)
(OVERLAPPING SHOUTING)
Hi.
Sorry to interrupt.
I'm Christopher Pike.
My world is called Earth.
And though it's far from here.
uh. my people and yours
are very much alike.
This is my world today.
But we were not always peaceful.
This is Earth in our 21st century.
Before everything went wrong.
It's a lot like your world today.
Recently I was
treated to a glimpse of my future.
It was not all I'd hoped.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
After all. what good is there
in knowing your future?
A friend of mine
asked me that recently and...
Didn't understand what he meant.
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
Until now.
I've seen my future.
Let me show you yours.
(DEVICE BEEPS)
Our conflict also started
with a fight for freedoms.
We called it the she Second Civil War.
then the Eugenics War.
and finally just World War III.
This was our last day.
The day the Earth we knew
ceased to exist.
What began as an eruption in one nation
ended in the eradication
of 600.000 species of animals and plants
and 30% of Earth's population.
Global suicide.
What we gave you
is the means to exterminate yourselves.
And from the looks of you.
you're gonna do it.
You'll use competing ideas of liberty
to bomb each other to rubble.
just like we did.
and then your last day
will look just like this.
Perhaps. somewhere.
all your ends are written
as indelibly as mine.
But I choose to believe
that your destinies are still your own.
Maybe that's why I'm here.
to remind you
of the power
of possibility.
Maybe that's the good
in seeing my future.
that I might remind you that.
right up until the very end.
life is to be worn gloriously.
Because. till our last moment.
the future's what we make it.
So...
go to war with each other.
Or...
join our Federation of Planets
and reach for the stars.
The choice is yours.
APRIL: Getting the Federation High Court
not to throw you all in jail
almost took more pull than I have.
And I have a lot of pull.
I had to go to the CNC personally
to get myself read into
what you people did on Discovery.
Hell of a job. Chris.
If I may ask. Admiral.
how did you convince Starfleet
our actions did not violate
General Order 1?
I used a loophole.
Since the council can't acknowledge
that the battle
ever actually took place...
It cannot acknowledge how
the people of Kiley 279 acquired warp.
Council's not happy about it.
They're doubling down.
renaming it the Prime Directive.
Well. that'll never stick.
Permission to return to Enterprise. sir.
That's up to you. Chris.
You planning on keeping the chair?
(INDISTINCT P.A. ANNOUNCEMENT)
You wanted to see me. Captain.
I should have told you. sir.
Tell me now.
The Gorn have a ritual.
The last one. the one who survives.
they send into space on a raft.
Like throwing a fish back. I suppose.
You're not really supposed to survive.
Dumb luck the King Jr. ran into me.
Una was an ensign on the King.
She helped me find my way back home.
She's the reason I joined Starfleet.
I was worried
that you would question my ability
to carry on the mission.
You were worried I wouldn't trust you.
Yes.
So you decided not to trust me instead.
I was wrong. I'm... I'm sorry.
Your record is spotless.
But
there's more to serving Starfleet
than just individual excellence.
Our ability to work together.
that's our greatest strength.
Other people are
challenging. for me.
Mmm.
You know how those domes got up here?
- No. sir.
- Well.
during World War Ill.
a group of scientists
sent seed pods into space.
to preserve them.
But when the war was over
and Earth had rebuilt.
the forests were too large
to bring home.
So. Starfleet built
its first base around them.
Even in space.
growth.
sometimes
remarkable growth.
is possible.
I'd like to offer you a commission
to join us on the Enterprise.
Sir?
PIKE: Captain's Log. Stardate 2259.42.
- (DEVICE CHIMES)
- Earth.
the dust and sky. is my hearth.
But Enterprise is my home.
We can go forward together.
knowing that
whatever shadows we bring with us.
they make the light all the brighter.
I am
a lucky man.
(BOATSWAIN'S WHISTLE BLOWS)
WOMAN: Captain on the bridge.
Crew rotation is complete. Captain.
Lieutenant Kirk is on his way
to the bridge. as you requested.
Thank you. Number One.
New security chief is in place.
Captain.
Departing Starbase 1. We are five by.
Starfleet Command. this is Enterprise.
Requesting warp clearance.
Ship systems are optimal.
(CHUCKLES) Oh. man.
Chris.
I mean. Captain.
PIKE: Samuel Kirk.
Welcome to Enterprise.
- How's the family?
- All fine. sir.
It's great to be here.
Well. you're posted to life sciences.
and he's your new boss.
We are cleared for warp. sir.
ORTEGAS: Course. Captain?
What's the mission?
Our mission?
We explore.
We seek out new life
and new civilizations.
We boldly go
where no one has gone before.
Cool.
Sir.
Let's take her out. Lieutenant Ortegas.
Warp factor 2.
Hit it.
(ENGINES POWERING UP)
(WHOOSHES)
(THEME MUSIC PLAYING)